I love the Internet.
انا احب الانترنت
It's true.
هذه حقيقة
Think about everything it has brought us.
فكر بكل شيئ احضرته لنا
Think about all the services we use,
فكر بكل الخدمات التي نستخدمها
all the connectivity,
كل الاتصالات
all the entertainment,
كل أنواع التسلية
all the business, all the commerce.
و كل أنواع الأعمال و التجارة.
And it's happening during our lifetimes.
و ان هذا يحصل خلال فترة حياتنا
I'm pretty sure that one day
انا متأكد جدا انه يوما ما
we'll be writing history books
سنكتب كتب التاريخ
hundreds of years from now. This time
بعد مئات السنين من الان .
our generation will be remembered
جيلنا سيتم تذكره
as the generation that got online,
بالجيل الذي اصبح متواصلا عبر الانترنت
the generation
الجيل الذي
that built something really and truly global.
بنى شيئا فاتنا و حقا عالمي
But yes, it's also true
لكن في نفس الوقت
that the Internet has problems, very serious problems,
تواجه الانترنت مشاكل ,مشاكل جدية جدا
problems with security
مشاكل مع أمن المعلومات
and problems with privacy.
ومشاكل مع خصوصية المستخدمين
I've spent my career
ولقد قضيت سنوات مهنتي
fighting these problems.
في مجابهة هذه المشاكل
So let me show you something.
لذا دعوني اريكم شيئا
This here
هذا هنا
is Brain.
هو (برين)
This is a floppy disk
هذا القرص المرن
-- five and a quarter-inch floppy disk
قرص ¼5 انش
infected by Brain.A.
مصاب بفيروس (برين. اي)
It's the first virus we ever found
انه اول فيروس وجدناه
for PC computers.
للحواسيب الشخصية
And we actually know
و في الواقع نحن نعلم
where Brain came from.
من اين اتى برين
We know because it says so
نحن نعلم لأنه يقول ذلك
inside the code.
داخل الشفرة
Let's take a look.
لنلقي نظرة
All right.
حسنا
That's the boot sector of an infected floppy,
هذا هو جزء الاقلاع من القرص المرن المصاب
and if we take a closer look inside,
و اذا اخذنا نظرة اقرب للداخل
we'll see that right there,
سوف نرى ذلك هنا
it says, "Welcome to the dungeon."
انه يقول"مرحبا بك في الزنزانة"
And then it continues,
و يواصل بعد ذلك
saying, 1986, Basit and Amjad.
يقول ,1986, بسيط و امجد
And Basit and Amjad are first names,
و بسيط و امجد هي اسماء اولى
Pakistani first names.
اسماء باكستانية
In fact, there's a phone number and an address in Pakistan.
في الواقع هنالك رقم هاتف و عنوان في باكستان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, 1986.
الان,1986
Now it's 2011.
و الان 2011
That's 25 years ago.
ذلك كان قبل 25 عاما
The PC virus problem is 25 years old now.
مشكلة فيروسات الحواسيب الشخصية لها 25 عاما الان
So half a year ago,
لذا قبل نصف عام
I decided to go to Pakistan myself.
قررت ان اذهب الى باكستان بنفسي
So let's see, here's a couple of photos I took while I was in Pakistan.
اذن دعونا نرى,هذه بعض الصور التي التقطتها عندما كنت في باكستان
This is from the city of Lahore,
هذه من مدينة لاهور
which is around 300 kilometers south
التي هي حوالي 300 كيلومتر جنوبا
from Abbottabad, where Bin Laden was caught.
من ابوتاباد حيث تم امساك بن لادن
Here's a typical street view.
هكذا يبدو الشارع
And here's the street or road leading to this building,
و هذا هو الشارع الذي يقود لهذا البناء
which is 730 Nizam block at Allama Iqbal Town.
منزل رقم 730 في حي نظام في بلدة الاما اقبال
And I knocked on the door.
و طرقت الباب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You want to guess who opened the door?
اتريدون ان تخمنو من فتح الباب؟
Basit and Amjad; they are still there.
بسيط و امجد ,مازالا هناك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So here standing up is Basit.
اذن هنا الواقف هو بسيط
Sitting down is his brother Amjad.
و الجالس هو اخوه امجد
These are the guys who wrote the first PC virus.
هؤلاء هم من كتب اول فيروس حاسوب شخصي
Now of course, we had a very interesting discussion.
الان طبعا ,لقد خضنا نقاش مثير جدا للاهتمام
I asked them why.
سألتهم لماذا.
I asked them how they feel about what they started.
سألتهم ما هو شعورهم تجاه ما بدؤوه
And I got some sort of satisfaction
و حصلت على بعض الرضا
from learning that both Basit and Amjad
من معرفة ان كلا بسيط و امجد
had had their computers infected dozens of times
قد أصيبت حواسيبهما بالفيروسات أكثر من مرة
by completely unrelated other viruses
وكانت فيروسات اخرى مختلفة كليا
over these years.
على مر هذه السنوات.
So there is some sort of justice
اذن هنالك نوع من العدالة
in the world after all.
في العالم فوق كل شيئ
Now, the viruses that we used to see
الان الفيروسات التي اعتدنا ان نراها
in the 1980s and 1990s
في الثمانينيات و التسعينيات
obviously are not a problem any more.
ليست مشكلة بعد الان
So let me just show you a couple of examples
لذا دعوني اريكم بعض الامثلة
of what they used to look like.
على ما كانو يبدون عليه
What I'm running here
ما اشغله هنا
is a system that enables me
هو نظام يمكنني
to run age-old programs on a modern computer.
من تشغيل برامج قديمة على حاسوب حديث
So let me just mount some drives. Go over there.
لذا دعوني فقط اركب بعض السواقات ,اذهب الى هناك
What we have here is a list of old viruses.
ما لدينا هنا هو قائمة بالفيروسات القديمة
So let me just run some viruses on my computer.
لذا دعوني فقط اشغل بعضها على حاسوبي
For example,
عل سبيل المثال
let's go with the Centipede virus first.
دعونا نشغل فيروس(ام اربع و اربعين) اولا
And you can see at the top of the screen,
و يمكنك ان ترى في اعلى الشاشة
there's a centipede scrolling across your computer
هنالك ام اربع و اربعين تزحف عبر حاسوبك
when you get infected by this one.
عندما تصاب بهذا
You know that you're infected
تعرف انك اصبت
because it actually shows up.
لانه في الواقع يظهر
Here's another one. This is the virus called Crash,
هذا واحد اخر هذا يسمى فيروس (كراش)
invented in Russia in 1992.
اخترع في روسيا في 1992
Let me show you one which actually makes some sound.
دعوني اريكم واحد في الواقع يشغل بعض الاصوات
(Siren noise)
(صوت صافرة انذار)
And the last example,
و اخر مثال
guess what the Walker virus does?
احزر ما يفعله فيروس (الماشي)
Yes, there's a guy walking across your screen
نعم هنالك شخص يمشي عبر شاشتك
once you get infected.
ما ان تتم اصابتك
So it used to be fairly easy to know
اذن كان من السهل معرفة
that you're infected by a virus,
انه تم اصابتك بفيروس
when the viruses were written by hobbyists
عندما كانت الفيروسات يبرمجها الهواة
and teenagers.
و المراهقين
Today, they are no longer being written
اليوم,انها لا تبرمج
by hobbyists and teenagers.
عن طريق الهواة و المراهقين
Today, viruses are a global problem.
اليوم ,الفيروسات مشكلة عالمية
What we have here in the background
ما لدينا هنا في الخلفية
is an example of our systems that we run in our labs,
مثال للانظمة التي نشغلها في مختبراتنا
where we track virus infections worldwide.
حيث نتعقب اصابات الفيروسات عالميا
So we can actually see in real time
لذا نحن نرى في الوقت الحقيقي
that we've just blocked viruses in Sweden and Taiwan
اننا قد اوقفنا فيروس في السويد و تايوان
and Russia and elsewhere.
و روسيا و اماكن اخرى
In fact, if I just connect back to our lab systems
في الواقع اذا اتصلت مرة اخرى بانظمة مختبراتنا
through the Web,
عن طريق الشبكة
we can see in real time
يمكننا ان نرى في الوقت الحقيقي
just some kind of idea of how many viruses,
فقط فكرة عن كم من الفيروسات
how many new examples of malware we find every single day.
كم من امثلة البرامج الخبيثة نجدها كل يوم
Here's the latest virus we've found,
هذا هو اخر فيروس اكتشفناه
in a file called Server.exe.
في ملف يدعى(server.exe)
And we found it right over here three seconds ago --
و وجدناه هنا قبل 3 ثواني
the previous one, six seconds ago.
الذي قبله, قبل 6 ثواني
And if we just scroll around,
و اذا مررنا عبر الصفحة
it's just massive.
انه فقط هائل
We find tens of thousands, even hundreds of thousands.
نجد عشرات الالاف حتى مئات الالاف
And that's the last 20 minutes of malware
و هذه هي اخر 20 دقيقة من البرامج الخبيثة
every single day.
كل يوم
So where are all these coming from then?
اذن من اين يأتي كل هذا؟
Well today, it's the organized criminal gangs
حسنا اليوم,انها عصابات اجرامية منظمة
writing these viruses
تبرمج هذه الفيروسات
because they make money with their viruses.
لأنهم يحصلون على المال من فيروساتهم
It's gangs like --
انها مثل عصابة
let's go to GangstaBucks.com.
لنذهب الى(gangstabucks.com)
This is a website operating in Moscow
هذا الموقع يعمل في موسكو
where these guys are buying infected computers.
حيث يشترون حواسيب مصابة
So if you are a virus writer
اذن اذا كنت مبرمج فيروسات
and you're capable of infecting Windows computers,
و كنت قادرا على اصابة حواسيب ويندوز
but you don't know what to do with them,
لكن لا تعرف ماذا تفعل بها
you can sell those infected computers --
بامكانك ان تبيع هذه الحواسيب المصابة
somebody else's computers -- to these guys.
حواسيب اشخاص اخرين لهؤلاء الاشخاص
And they'll actually pay you money for those computers.
و هم في الواقع سوف يدفعوا لك مال مقابل هذه الحواسيب
So how do these guys then monetize
اذن كيف يحول هؤلاء الاشخاص
those infected computers?
الحواسيب المصابة الى مال؟
Well there's multiple different ways,
حسنا هنالك عدة طرق مختلفة
such as banking trojans, which will steal money from your online banking accounts
مثل احصنة طروادة البنكية,التي تسرق المال من حسابك البنكي على الشبكة
when you do online banking,
عندما تؤدي اعمال بنكية على الشبكة
or keyloggers.
او مسجلات المفاتيح
Keyloggers silently sit on your computer, hidden from view,
مسجلات المفاتيح تجلس في الحاسوب بصمت ,مخفية عن الانظار
and they record everything you type.
وهي تسجل اي شيئ تطبعه
So you're sitting on your computer and you're doing Google searches.
اذن انت جالس الى حاسوبك تبحث في قوقل
Every single Google search you type
كل بحث تجريه في قوقل
is saved and sent to the criminals.
يحفظ و يرسل الى المجرمين
Every single email you write is saved and sent to the criminals.
كل بريد الكتروني تكتبه يحفظ و يرسل الى المجرمين
Same thing with every single password and so on.
نفس الشيئ مع كل كلمة سر و ما الى ذلك
But the thing that they're actually looking for most
لكن الشيئ الذي يبحثون عنه اكثر
are sessions where you go online
هي الفترات الزمنية عندما تكون على الشبكة
and do online purchases in any online store.
و تشترى على الشبكة في اي متجر الكتروني
Because when you do purchases in online stores,
لانه عنما تشتري في المتاجر الالكترونية
you will be typing in your name, the delivery address,
سوف تكتب اسمك و عنوان التسليم
your credit card number and the credit card security codes.
رقم بطاقتك الائتمانية ورقم المرور السري لها
And here's an example of a file
و هذا مثال لملف
we found from a server a couple of weeks ago.
وجدناه في خادم قبل عدة اسابيع
That's the credit card number,
هذا رقم بطاقة الائتمان
that's the expiration date, that's the security code,
هذا تاريخ نهاية الصلاحية ,و هذا الرقم السري
and that's the name of the owner of the card.
و هذا اسم مالك البطاقة
Once you gain access to other people's credit card information,
ما ان تحصل معلومات بطاقة الائتمان لاناس اخرون
you can just go online and buy whatever you want
تستطيع ان تدخل الشبكة و تشتري ما تريد
with this information.
بهذه المعلومات
And that, obviously, is a problem.
و هذا من الواضح مشكلة
We now have a whole underground marketplace
الان لدينا سوق اسود كامل
and business ecosystem
و انظمة اعمال اقتصادية
built around online crime.
مبنية حو ل الجريمة الالكترونية
One example of how these guys
مثال على كيف
actually are capable of monetizing their operations:
يستطيع هؤلاء الاشخاص تنفيذ عملياتهم
we go and have a look at the pages of INTERPOL
ذهبنا و اخذنا نظرة على صفحات الانتربول
and search for wanted persons.
و بحثنا عن اشخاص مطلوبين
We find guys like Bjorn Sundin, originally from Sweden,
وجدنا اشخاص مثل (بيجورن سندين) في الاصل من السويد
and his partner in crime,
و شريكه في الجريمة
also listed on the INTERPOL wanted pages,
ايضا في صفحات المطلوبين في الانتربول
Mr. Shaileshkumar Jain,
السيد(شيلشكومار جاين)
a U.S. citizen.
مواطن امريكي
These guys were running an operation called I.M.U.,
هؤلاء الشباب كانو يديرون عملية اسمها(آي ام يو)
a cybercrime operation through which they netted millions.
عملية جريمة الكترونية حيث كان صافي ربحهم الملايين
They are both right now on the run.
الان كلاهما هاربان
Nobody knows where they are.
لا احد يعلم اين هما
U.S. officials, just a couple of weeks ago,
المسؤولين الامريكيين فقط قبل عدة اسابيع
froze a Swiss bank account
جمدو حساب في بنك سويسري
belonging to Mr. Jain,
يعود الى السيد جاين
and that bank account had 14.9 million U.S. dollars on it.
و ذلك الحساب كان فيه 14.9 مليون دولار امريكي
So the amount of money online crime generates
اذن كمية المال التي تولدها الجريمة الالكترونية
is significant.
كبيرة
And that means that the online criminals
وذلك يعني ان المجرمين الالكترونيين
can actually afford to invest into their attacks.
بأمكانهم ان يستثمروا في هجماتهم
We know that online criminals
نحن نعلم ان المجرمين الالكترونيين
are hiring programmers, hiring testing people,
يوظفون مبرمجين,يوظفون اشخاص للاختبار
testing their code,
لاختبار شفراتهم
having back-end systems with SQL databases.
لديهم انظمة حديثة مع انظمة قواعد بيانات(اس كيو ال)
And they can afford to watch how we work --
و يستطيعون تحمل ثمن مشاهدة كيف نعمل
like how security people work --
مثل كيف يعمل رجال الامن
and try to work their way around
و يحاولون ايجاد طريقهم حول
any security precautions we can build.
اي اجراء امني نستطيع بناءه .
They also use the global nature of Internet
هم ايضا يستخدمون الطبيعة العالمية للانترنت
to their advantage.
لمصلحتهم
I mean, the Internet is international.
انا اعني ان الانترنت عالمي
That's why we call it the Internet.
لهذا يسمي الانترنت
And if you just go and take a look
و اذا ذهبنا واخذنا نظرة
at what's happening in the online world,
على ما يحدث في العالم الافتراضي
here's a video built by Clarified Networks,
هنا فيديو صنع بواسطة كلارفيد نتوركس
which illustrates how one single malware family is able to move around the world.
حيث يوضح كيف ان عائلة برامج خبيثة واحدة تستطيع ان تتحرك حول العالم
This operation, believed to be originally from Estonia,
هذه العملية يعتقد انها بدأت في الاصل من استونيا
moves around from one country to another
تتحرك من بلد الى اخر
as soon as the website is tried to shut down.
حالما يحاول شخص إغلاق الموقع
So you just can't shut these guys down.
لذا لا يمكنك ايقاف هؤلاء الاشخاص
They will switch from one country to another,
سوف يتحولون من بلد الى اخر
from one jurisdiction to another --
من سلطة قضائية الى اخرى
moving around the world,
يتحركون حول العالم
using the fact that we don't have the capability
مستخدمين حقيقة اننا لا نملك القدرة
to globally police operations like this.
على عمليات بوليسية عالمية مثل هذه
So the Internet is as if
اذن الانترنت مثل
someone would have given free plane tickets
اعطاء شخص تذاكر طائرة مجانية
to all the online criminals of the world.
الى كل المجرمين الالكترونيين في العالم
Now, criminals who weren't capable of reaching us before
المجرمين الذين كانو لا يستطيعون الوصول لنا من قبل
can reach us.
يستطيعون وصولنا
So how do you actually go around finding online criminals?
اذن كيف تذهب حقا لايجاد المجرمين على الشبكة؟
How do you actually track them down?
كيف تتعقبهم حقا
Let me give you an example.
دعوني اعطيكم مثالا
What we have here is one exploit file.
ما لدينا هنا هو ملف مصاب واحد
Here, I'm looking at the Hex dump of an image file,
هنا انا انظر الى مكب الهكس لملف صورة
which contains an exploit.
الذي يحتوي على تهديد امني
And that basically means, if you're trying to view this image file on your Windows computer,
وذلك يعني اساسا اذا اردت رؤية هذه الصورة في حاسوب ويندوز الخاص بك
it actually takes over your computer and runs code.
في الواقع هي تسيطر على حاسوبك وتشغل شفرات
Now, if you'll take a look at this image file --
الان اذا نظرت الى ملف الصورة هذا
well there's the image header,
حسنا هنالك بادئة صورة
and there the actual code of the attack starts.
و هنا حيث تبدأ شفرة الهجوم
And that code has been encrypted,
و هذه الشفرة تم ترميزها
so let's decrypt it.
اذن لنفك الترميز
It has been encrypted with XOR function 97.
لقد تم ترميزها باستخدام دالة XOR 97
You just have to believe me,
يجب فقط ان تصدقوني
it is, it is.
انها كذلك,انها كذلك
And we can go here
و يمكننا الذهاب هنا
and actually start decrypting it.
و نبدأ حقا في فك الترميز
Well the yellow part of the code is now decrypted.
حسن الجزء الاصفر من الشفر هو الان غير مرمز
And I know, it doesn't really look much different from the original.
و انا اعلم انه لا يبدو مختلفا كثيرا من الاصل
But just keep staring at it.
لكن فقط واصلو التحديق به
You'll actually see that down here
سوف ترى ذلك حقا في الاسفل هنا
you can see a Web address:
تستطيع ان ترى عنوان ويب هنا
unionseek.com/d/ioo.exe
unionseek.com/d/ioo.exe
And when you view this image on your computer
و عندما تعرض هذه الصورة في حاسوبك
it actually is going to download and run that program.
هي في الواقع سوف تقوم بتنزيل و تشغيل ذلك البرنامج
And that's a backdoor which will take over your computer.
وذلك هو الباب الخلفي الذي سوف يسيطر على حاسوبك
But even more interestingly,
لكن باكثر اثارة للاهتمام
if we continue decrypting,
اذا واصلنا فك الترميز
we'll find this mysterious string,
سوف نجد هذه الجملة الغامض
which says O600KO78RUS.
التي تقول O600KO78RUS
That code is there underneath the encryption
تلك الشفرة هناك اسفل الترميز
as some sort of a signature.
كنوع من التوقيع
It's not used for anything.
انها ليست مستخدمة لاي شيئ
And I was looking at that, trying to figure out what it means.
و انا كنت انظر لاى ذلك ومحاولا معرفة ماذا تعني
So obviously I Googled for it.
لذا طبعا قمت بالبحث عنها في قوقل
I got zero hits; wasn't there.
لم اجد اي نتائج ,لم تكن هناك
So I spoke with the guys at the lab.
لذا تحدثت مع الشباب في المختبر
And we have a couple of Russian guys in our labs,
و لدينا شخصان روسيان في مختبراتنا
and one of them mentioned,
و ذكر احدهما
well, it ends in RUS like Russia.
حسنا انها تنتهي ب(rus) مثل روسيا
And 78 is the city code
و 78 هو رمز المدينة
for the city of St. Petersburg.
لمدينة سانت بيترسبرغ
For example, you can find it from some phone numbers
عل سببيل المثال يمكن ان تجدها من بعض ارقام الهواتف
and car license plates and stuff like that.
و لوحات السيارات و اشياء مثل هذه
So I went looking for contacts in St. Petersburg,
لذا ذهبت للبحث عن جهات اتصال في سانت بيترسبيرغ
and through a long road,
و خلال طريق طويل
we eventually found this one particular website.
في النهاية وجدنا موقع معين
Here's this Russian guy who's been operating online for a number of years
هنا هذا الشاب الروسي الذي كان يعمل على الشبكة منذ عدة سنوات
who runs his own website,
الذي يدير موقعه الخاص
and he runs a blog under the popular Live Journal.
و يدير مدونة تحت مجلة لايف جورنال
And on this blog, he blogs about his life,
و في هذه المدونة ,يدون عن حياته
about his life in St. Petersburg --
عن حياته في سانت بيترسبيرغ
he's in his early 20s --
هو في بداية العشرينات من عمره
about his cat,
عن قطته
about his girlfriend.
عن صديقته
And he drives a very nice car.
و هو يقود سيارة جميلة جدا
In fact, this guy drives
في الواقع هذا الشاب يقود
a Mercedes-Benz S600
مرسيدس بنز اس600
V12
12 صمام
with a six-liter engine
بمحرك سعة 6 ليترات
with more than 400 horsepower.
و قوة 400 حصان
Now that's a nice car for a 20-something year-old kid in St. Petersburg.
الان هذه سيارة جميلة لشاب في العشرينات في سانت بيترسبيرغ
How do I know about this car?
كيف اعلم عن سيارته؟
Because he blogged about the car.
لانه دون عنها
He actually had a car accident.
في الواقع لقد حصل معه حادث
In downtown St. Petersburg,
في وسط المدينة في سانت بيترسبيرغ
he actually crashed his car into another car.
في الواقع هو صدم سيارته بسيارة اخرى
And he put blogged images about the car accident --
ووضع صور في المدونة عن حادث سيارته
that's his Mercedes --
هذه هي المرسيدس الخاصة به
right here is the Lada Samara he crashed into.
و هنا اللادا سمارا التي صدمها
And you can actually see that the license plate of the Samara
و تستطيع حقا رؤية لوحة السمارا
ends in 78RUS.
تنتهي ب 78RUS
And if you actually take a look at the scene picture,
و اذا اخذت نظرة على صورة المشهد
you can see that the plate of the Mercedes
تستطيع ان ترى لوحة المرسيدس
is O600KO78RUS.
هي O600KO78RUS
Now I'm not a lawyer,
الان انا لست محامي
but if I would be,
لكن اذا كنت كذلك
this is where I would say, "I rest my case."
هنا حيث اقول "انا اختم قضيتي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what happens when online criminals are caught?
اذن ماذا يحدث عندما يتم القبض على المجرمين الاكترونيين
Well in most cases it never gets this far.
حسنا في معظم الحالات لا تصل الى هذا البعد
The vast majority of the online crime cases,
الغالبية العظمى لقضايا الجرائم الالكترونية
we don't even know which continent the attacks are coming from.
نحن لا ندري من اي قارة تاتي الهجمات
And even if we are able to find online criminals,
و حتى اذا استطعنا ايجاد المجرمين
quite often there is no outcome.
في الغالب لا يوجد ناتج
The local police don't act, or if they do, there's not enough evidence,
الشرطة المحلية لا تتصرف و اذا فعلو لا يوجد دليل كافي
or for some reason we can't take them down.
او لسبب ما لا نستطيع القبض عليهم
I wish it would be easier;
انا اتمنى ان تكون اسهل
unfortunately it isn't.
لسوء الحظ هي ليست كذلك
But things are also changing
لكن الاشياء ايضا تتغير
at a very rapid pace.
بسرعة كبيرة جدا
You've all heard about things like Stuxnet.
كلكم سمعتم باشياء مثل دودة ستكسنت
So if you look at what Stuxnet did
اذن اذا نظرتم الى ما فعلته ستكسنت
is that it infected these.
هي اصابة هذا المتحكمة
That's a Siemens S7-400 PLC,
تلك المتحكمة المبرمجة من شركة سيمينس
programmable logic [controller].
متحكم حاسوب مبرمج منطقيا
And this is what runs our infrastructure.
و هذا هو ما يدير بنياتنا التحتية
This is what runs everything around us.
هذا ما يدير كل شيئ حولنا
PLC's, these small boxes which have no display,
المتحكمات المبرمجة هذه الصناديق الصغيرة التي ليس لديها شاشة
no keyboard,
ولا لوحة مفاتيح
which are programmed, are put in place, and they do their job.
تبرمج وتوضع في مكانها وتؤدي عملها
For example, the elevators in this building
على سبيل المثال المصاعد في هذا المبنى
most likely are controlled by one of these.
على الاغلب يتم التحكم فيها عن طريق واحد من هذه
And when Stuxnet infects one of these,
و عندما يصيب ستكس نت احدى هذه
that's a massive revolution
هذه ثورة عظيمة
on the kinds of risks we have to worry about.
في نوع الخطر الذي يجب ان نقلق بشأنه
Because everything around us is being run by these.
لان كل شيئ حولنا يتم تشغيله بهذه
I mean, we have critical infrastructure.
انا اعني ان لدينا بنية تحتية حرجة
You go to any factory, any power plant,
اذهب الى اي مصنع اي محطة طاقة
any chemical plant, any food processing plant,
اي مصنع كيميائي اي مصنع اغذية
you look around --
انظر حولك
everything is being run by computers.
كل شيئ يتم تشغيله بالحواسيب
Everything is reliant on these computers working.
كل شيئ يعتمد على هذه الحواسيب ان تعمل
We have become very reliant
نحن اصبحنا معتمدين جدا
on Internet,
على الانترنت
on basic things like electricity, obviously,
على اشياء اساسية مثل الكهرباء
on computers working.
على الحواسيب ان تعمل
And this really is something
و هذا حقا شيئ
which creates completely new problems for us.
يخلق مشاكل جديدة لنا
We must have some way
يجب ان نجد طريقة
of continuing to work
لمواصلة عملنا
even if computers fail.
حتى اذا فشلت الحواسيب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So preparedness means that we can do stuff
اذن الجاهزية تعني ان نستطيع عمل اشياء
even when the things we take for granted
حتى لو كانت الاشياء التى نأخذها من الامور المسلم بها
aren't there.
ليست هنا
It's actually very basic stuff --
انها في الواقع اشياء اساسية جدا
thinking about continuity, thinking about backups,
التفكير في الاستمرارية,التفكير في النسخ الاحتياطية
thinking about the things that actually matter.
التفكير في الاشياء التي تهم حقا
Now I told you --
الان انا اخبركم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I love the Internet. I do.
انا احب الانترنت,احبها
Think about all the services we have online.
فكروا بكل الخدمات التي لدينا على الشبكة
Think about if they are taken away from you,
فكروا اذا اخذت منا
if one day you don't actually have them
اذا في يوم ما ليست لديك حقا
for some reason or another.
لسبب او لاخر
I see beauty in the future of the Internet,
انا ارى الجمال في مستقبل الانترنت
but I'm worried
لكن انا قلق
that we might not see that.
اننا ربما لن نستطيع رؤية ذلك
I'm worried that we are running into problems
انا قلق اننا نجرى الى داخل المشكلات
because of online crime.
بسبب الجريمة الالكترونية
Online crime is the one thing
الجريمة الالكترونية هي شيئ
that might take these things away from us.
يمكن ان يأخذ هذه الاشياء منا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I've spent my life
انا قضيت حياتي
defending the Net,
في الدفاع عن الشبكة
and I do feel that if we don't fight online crime,
و انا اشعر انه اذا لم نحارب الجريمة الالكترونية
we are running a risk of losing it all.
نحن نخاطر بخسارته كله
We have to do this globally,
يجب ان نفعل ذلك بشكل عالمي
and we have to do it right now.
ويجب ان نفعلها الان
What we need
ما نحتاجه
is more global, international law enforcement work
هو قوى امنية اكثر عالمية
to find online criminal gangs --
للعثور على عصابات الجريمة الالكترونية
these organized gangs
هذه العصابات المنظمة
that are making millions out of their attacks.
التي تربح الملايين من هجماتها
That's much more important
ذلك اكثر اهمية
than running anti-viruses or running firewalls.
من تشغيل مضادات الفيروسات او جدران الحماية
What actually matters
ما يهم حقا
is actually finding the people behind these attacks,
هو العثور على الاشخاص خلف هذه الهجمات
and even more importantly,
و اكثر اهمية
we have to find the people
يجب ان نجد الاشخاص
who are about to become
الذين هم على وشك ان يصبحوا
part of this online world of crime,
جزء من عالم الجريمة الالكتروني هذا
but haven't yet done it.
لكن لم يفعلو بعد
We have to find the people with the skills,
يجب ان نجد اشخاص بالمهارات
but without the opportunities
لكن بدون الفرص
and give them the opportunities
و اعطائهم الفرص
to use their skills for good.
لاستخدام مهاراتهم للخير
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)